A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial records, Issue Books, Series 17 FA363
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson A. Rockefeller gubernatorial records, Issue Books, Series 17
1959-1964
Rockefeller Archive Center
Boyd, Joseph H.
Perkins, Roswell B.
Cannon, James M.
Morrow, Hugh
New York (State). State Commission for Human Rights
New York (State). Governor (1959-1973: Rockefeller)
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
Ronan, William J. (William John)
New York (State). Dept. of Civil Service
Whitman, Ann
FA363
37 document box(es)
Biographical/Historical note
Nelson A. Rockefeller served as governor of New York from January 1, 1959, to December 18, 1973. He was the first person elected to four consecutive four-year terms as a state governor.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 15 17
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for scholarly research, except where particular restrictions are noted.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Arrangement note
This series is divided into two subseries:
Subseries 1 - 1964 Presidential Election, 1959-1964 Subseries 2 - First Gubernatorial Term, 1958-1962
Scope and Contents note
SCOPE AND CONTENT
This series consists of more than 80 volumes of aggregated factual material on both national and state issues. The Issue Books contain statements and press releases issued by the Gubernatorial Press Office in response to important political and policy issues, as well as other substantive material. Governor Rockefeller also had many experts write background papers on various subjects relevant to the two campaigns. In most cases, these papers are coupled with summary papers or supporting memoranda for Governor Rockefeller to assist him with the formulation of a position on the issue.
Other Finding Aids note
Detailed finding aids for each series of this collection are available:
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Appointments Office (FA353)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Assembly and Senate Memos (FA354)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Joseph H. Boyd (FA355)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, James Cannon (FA356)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Affirmative Action (N. Lee Cook) (FA357)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Counsel's Office (FA358)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York State Committee to Reelect the President (FA359)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Jerry A. Danzig (FA360)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Executive Chamber (FA361)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, 55th Street (FA362)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Arthur Massolo (FA364)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Hugh Morrow (FA242)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York Office (FA365)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Civil Service Resolutions (Charles H. Palmer) (FA366)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Political Files (FA367)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Press Office (FA368)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Public Relations (FA369)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Departmental Reports (FA370)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, William J. Ronan (FA371)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Speeches (FA372)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Diane Van Wie (FA373)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Ann C. Whitman, Gubernatorial (FA374)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Gene Wyckoff (FA375)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York Republican State Fund Raising Reports (FA376)
Public relations; State governments -- United States; Presidential candidates -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Public policy; United States; Vice-Presidents -- United States; Government policy; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1962; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1966; Civil service; Civil service -- New York (State); Economics; Federal government -- United States; Arms control; Arms control -- United States; Civil defense; Civil defense -- United States; International economic relations; Human rights; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1970; Affirmative action programs -- New York (State); Latin America; Legislation -- New York (State); International relations; International relations -- United States; Political campaigns -- United States; Political science; New York (N.Y.); New York (State); Presidential campaigns -- United States; Boyd, Joseph H.; Perkins, Roswell B.; Cannon, James M.; Morrow, Hugh; New York (State). State Commission for Human Rights; New York (State). Governor (1959-1973: Rockefeller); Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich); Ronan, William J. (William John); Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); New York (State). Dept. of Civil Service; Whitman, Ann
- 1964 Presidential Election, 1959-1964; 1; 9.2 Cubic Feet
  Scope and Contents note
  The volumes in this subseries contain memoranda from Governor Rockefeller's staff and advisors. Much of the material was prepared under the supervision of Roswell B. Perkins, one of Rockefeller's chief advisors. Found throughout the volumes are draft "Platform Planks" submitted for consideration in the 1964 Republican Party Platform, as well as selections from the "Current Positions Notebook," which outlined Governor Rockefeller's stands on a variety of issues. This subseries also includes many background papers written by consultants hired by Governor Rockefeller. The material in this subseries was primarily gathered for the 1964 Presidential election, and therefore a majority of the material contains analyses of Kennedy and Johnson administration proposals and stands on issues, as well as evaluations of positions held by Senator Barry M. Goldwater. Campaign-related materials (pamphlets, position cards) are also found in this series.
  - Volume 1 - General Materials - Domestic and Foreign, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Tab 1 Position Papers - Domestic Issues, June 1960 -- full position papers primarily drafted by Roswell Perkins and Barbara Jones. The majority of the papers also contain summaries of background papers written on the issue. Agriculture Atoms for Peace Civil Rights Education (Higher) Education (Elementary & Secondary) Health Health Insurance for the Aged Highways Housing
  - Volume 1 - General Materials - Domestic and Foreign, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Tab 1 continued Position Papers - Domestic Issues, June 1960 -- full position papers primarily drafted by Roswell Perkins and Barbara Jones. The majority of the papers also contain summaries of background papers written on the issue. Inflation Labor Natural Resources Power Public Finance Recession Management Trade Relations & Anti-Trust Transportation
    Tab 2 Short Summaries of Domestic Position Papers, June 12, 1960 -- brief summaries of position papers, primarily written for NAR appearance on Open End program.
  - Volume 1 - General Materials - Domestic and Foreign, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Tab 3 Draft Platform Planks, June 19-21, 1960 - prepared by Roswell Perkins and Emmet Hughes, to help carry out recommendations made by Perkins in a memorandum concerning the first platform draft. Foreign Policy National Defense Labor & Commerce Agriculture and Natural Resources Education, Science & Technology Government Finance & Administration Civil Rights & Immigration Human Affairs
    Tab 4 NAR Statement, "A Republican Approach to the Great Issues," July 11, 1960 - published booklet in which NAR detailed his views on the issues confronting the Republican Party in the 1960s.
  - Volume 2 - General Materials - Domestic and Foreign, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Tab 5 Comments on Draft Republican Party Platform, July 14, 1960 -- two part commentary on the differences in the platform from NAR positions and "other comments of substance."
    Tab 6 NAR - Nixon Statement, 1960 Republican Platform, July 23, 1960 -- published statements of NAR and Vice President Richard Nixon, issued after the two reached an agreement on the 1960 Republican Party Platform.
    Tab 7 Inconsistencies in the Democratic Platform, August 1960 -- statements identifying conflicts in the Democratic Platform as compared to initiatives and actions of the Democratic Party.
    Tab 8 Analysis of the Republican and Democratic Platforms, September 9, 1960 -- comparison of the two party platforms.
    Tab 9 Suggested NAR Statement, Comparison of Republican and Democratic Platforms, September 12, 1960
    Tab 10 Analysis of 1960 Campaign, November 30, 1960 -- positions of Senator Kennedy and Vice President Nixon on issues in the 1960 presidential campaign, and positions of NAR on same issues along with suggested strategies for campaigning. Domestic Affairs Agriculture Automation Depressed Areas Economic Growth Education Inflation Labor Public Power Taxation Civil Rights Housing Health Natural Resources
  - Volume 2 - General Materials - Domestic and Foreign, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Tab 10 continued Analysis of 1960 Campaign, November 30, 1960 -- positions of Senator Kennedy and Vice President Nixon on issues in the 1960 presidential campaign, and positions of NAR on same issues along with suggested strategies for campaigning. Foreign Affairs Africa Communist China Eastern Europe Middle East Latin America United Nations Foreign Economic Aid Foreign Trade Chinese Off-Shore Islands National Defense Defense Alliances Nuclear Testing Arms Control Defense Department Reorganization Western Europe Regional Confederations Other Instruments of Foreign Policy
  - Volume 3 - General Materials - Domestic and Foreign, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Tab 11 NAR Briefing Papers, Thursday Night Television Appearance, January 11, 1962 -- briefing material summarized for NAR appearance on television.
    Tab 12 Memorandum, Summary of Proposals Contained in Kennedy State of the Union Message, January 18, 1962 -- memoranda prepared by Roswell Perkins in response to President Kennedy's State of the Union Address, delivered January 11, 1962.
    Tab 13 Position Papers, NAR Meeting with New York Republican Congressional Delegation, June 27, 1962 -- position papers for NAR on National Domestic Issues, Foreign and Defense Issues, and State Issues to be used in meeting with the New York State Republican Congressional Delegation.
  - Volume 3 - General Materials - Domestic and Foreign, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Tab 14 Draft NAR Statement, "Basic Beliefs of Republicans," July 3, 1962 -- statement for NAR to use in meeting with non-incumbent Congressional candidates.
    Tab 15 Current Positions Notebook, October 16, 1962 -- position papers for NAR. Some are indicative of a position NAR has stated publicly, while others are recommendations offered by Roswell Perkins or Henry Kissinger. Domestic Affairs Aged-General/Aged-Medical Care Agriculture Budget Civil Rights Economic Growth: Anti-Recession Education Health Housing and Urban Development Juvenile Delinquency Labor Narcotics Taxation Transportation Welfare Foreign Policy Central Europe Berlin Western European Defense Soviet Union Eastern Europe Cuba Southeast Asia - General South Vietnam Laos China Indonesia and Dutch New Guinea Iran Middle East Nuclear Testing Arms Control and Disarmament Defense Civil Defense Foreign Trade
    Tab 16 Current Positions Cards, October 25, 1962 -- speech cards with brief summaries and "talking points" for NAR.
  - Volume 4 - General Materials - Domestic and Foreign, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Tab 17 Background Paper, Summary Analysis of 1963 Presidential Messages, March 6, 1963 -- memoranda submitted to NAR by John Deardourff summarizing the eleven messages submitted to Congress by President Kennedy.
    Tab 18 Rockefeller on the Issues, Summary of NAR State Positions, prepared by Barbara Jones (September 1963) -- views of NAR as expressed in his speeches. Credo The National Economy Human and Social Concerns of Government
  - Volume 4 - General Materials - Domestic and Foreign, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Tab 18 continued Rockefeller on the Issues, Summary of NAR State Positions, prepared by Barbara Jones (September 1963) -- views of NAR as expressed in his speeches. Making Democracy Work The Republican Party: Its Principles and Philosophy Foreign Policy
  - Volume 1 - General Materials - Domestic and Foreign (partial copy), 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Volume 2 - General Materials - Domestic and Foreign (copy 2), 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Volume 2 - General Materials - Domestic and Foreign (copy 2), 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Volume 3 - General Materials - Domestic and Foreign (copy 2), 1961-1964 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Volume 3 - General Materials - Domestic and Foreign (copy 2), 1961-1964 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Volume 4 - General Materials - Domestic and Foreign (copy 2), 1961-1964 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Volume 4 - General Materials - Domestic and Foreign (copy 2), 1961-1964 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Volume 5 - General Materials - Domestic and Foreign, 1961-1964 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Tab 19 Questions and Answers for "U.S. News and World Report," September 5, 1966 -- responses given by NAR for interview for news magazine. General Issues: 1964 Issues; Radical Right; Differences with Goldwater; Differences with Kennedy; Self-Description Foreign Policy Issues: Cuba; Vietnam; NATO; Latin America; Foreign Aid; Nuclear Test Ban Domestic Policy Issues: Civil Rights; Economic Growth; Tax Cut; Fiscal Integrity; Education; Agriculture; Transportation; Right-to-Work; Emergency Strikes; Welfare; Federal-State Relations; Civil Defense; Federal Aid for Parochial Schools; Medical Care for the Aged Political Q & A
    Tab 20 NAR Interview, "U.S. News & World Report," September 23, 1963 -- copy of published interview.
    Tab 21 Summary of NAR Proposals on Foreign Affairs and Defense, October 1963 -- NAR public positions on issues of Foreign Affairs and Defense.
  - Volume 5 - General Materials - Domestic and Foreign, 1961-1964 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Tab 22 NAR Answers to Questions Presented by Associated Press, October 15, 1963
    Tab 23 NAR Briefing Materials for "Issues and Answers," October 17, 1963 -- materials prepared for NAR in advance of television appearance.
    Tab 24 Summary Positions Notebook (December 1963) Foreign Arms Control Communist China Cuba Foreign Aid Germany Indonesian Involvement in Malaysian Affairs Latin America Middle East NATO and European Integration Nuclear Testing Relations with the Soviet Union Sino-Soviet Split United Nations Vietnam Withdrawal of U.S. Forces from Europe Domestic
  - Volume 6 - General Materials - Domestic and Foreign, 1961-1964 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    Tab 25 Campaign Research Kit, Statements and Record of NAR on Major Issues, Summarized to January 1, 1964 -- published booklet of positions held by NAR.
    Tab 26 NAR One-Minute Spot Television Commercials, January 18, 1964 -- scripts for NAR political advertisements. Tab 27 NAR Additional One-Minute Spot Television Commercials, January 31, 1964 -- scripts for NAR political advertisements.
    Tab 28 NAR "Positive" One-Minute Spot Television Commercials, February 1, 1964 -- scripts for NAR political advertisements stressing a positive approach and the Democratic failures. These ads were not directed at Senator Goldwater.
    Tab 29 NAR One-Minute Spot Television Commercials, February 11, 1964 -- additional scripts for positive advertisements.
    Tab 30 NAR Answers to Questions Presented by the California Republican Assembly, February 27, 1964 -- published booklet of responses.
    Tab 31 NAR Answers to Questions Presented by the "Manchester (N.H.) Union-Leader," February 29, 1964
    Tab 32 NAR Statement, "The Future of the Republican Party," March 30, 1964 -- press release of remarks made by NAR at Bend Community College, Bend, Oregon.
    Tab 33 NAR Statement, "Differences with Democrats," March 30, 1964 -- press release of remarks made by NAR at Ontario Chamber of Commerce Breakfast, Ontario, Oregon.
    Tab 34 Taft, NAR, Goldwater Comparison on Domestic Issues, April 1964 -- campaign brochure outlining positions held by Senator Robert A. Taft (R-Ohio), Senator Barry Goldwater (R-Arizona), and NAR.
    Tab 35 Major Speech Outlines, april 3, 1964 -- suggested "talking points" on Domestic and Foreign Issues for NAR to be used in speeches.
  - Volume 6 - General Materials - Domestic and Foreign, 1961-1964 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    Tab 36 Topics for Five-Minute Spot Commercials, April 6, 1964 -- suggested issues to be addressed in political advertisements.
    Tab 37 Platform Analysis Notebook, May 1964 -- 1960 Republican Party Platform with suggestions for 1964 platform positions.
    Tab 38 NAR Answers to Questions Presented by the San Francisco "Monitor," May 7, 1964 -- NAR interview with the official paper of the Archdiocese of San Francisco and of the Diocese of Stockton and Santa Rosa.
    Tab 39 NAR Statement, "As a Republican, I Believe...," May 11, 1964 -- published brochure of NAR positions on issues affecting the United States and the Republican Party.
    Tab 40 Fact Sheet Notebook, May 11, 1964 -- brief summary positions of major issues.
    Tab 41 Kuchel Memorandum and Analysis, May 15, 1964 -- analysis of twenty-five Congressional votes cast by Senator Goldwater.
  - Volume 7 - General Materials - Domestic and Foreign, 1961-1964 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    Tab 42 Eisenhower Statement and Comparison with Rockefeller and Goldwater Statements and Record, May 27, 1964 -- evaluation of former President Eisenhower's statement of May 24, 1964, as compared with statements of NAR and Senator Goldwater.
    Tab 43 Draft Republican Platform "Planks," June 4, 1964 -- suggested materials to be used in formation of the 1964 Republican Party Platform.
    Tab 44 Draft "Model" Platform, June 18, 1964 -- suggested preliminary draft of 1964 Republican Party Platform.
    Tab 45 Evaluation of Goldwater "Blue Book," June 19, 1964 -- analysis of Goldwater campaign brochure, "Goldwater Speaks Out on the Issues."
  - Volume 7 - General Materials - Domestic and Foreign, 1961-1964 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    Tab 46 Domestic Issues Platform Materials, June 25, 1964 -- suggested issue positions and language for inclusion in the platform.
    Tab 47 Draft "One Page" Planks, Done for Senator Scott, June 30, 1964 -- one paragraph suggestions of language for inclusion in the platform.
    Tab 48 Possible Insertions and Amendments to Platform -- Domestic Issues, July 1, 1964
    Tab 49 Revised Set of Draft "Model" Platform Planks, July 6, 1964
    Tab 50 NAR Statement before Platform Committee, July 7, 1964 -- NAR speech to the Committee on Resolutions of the 1964 Republican National Convention.
    Tab 51 NAR Statement, Suggestion for Consideration by the Platform Committee, July 7, 1964 -- written suggestions made by NAR for inclusion in the 1964 Republican Party Platform.
    Tab 52 "Moderate" Platform Planks Submitted to Platform Committee by Senator Scott and Background Material on Planks, July 9 & 10, 1964
    Tab 53 Minority Views and Amendments Submitted to the Platform Committee by Senator Scott, July 13, 1964
  - Volume 8 - Foreign Policy, General, 1959-1964 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    Tab 1 Background Paper, Status of the Cold War, prepared by William Kintner, December 17, 1959 -- observations on Communist attitudes and tactics in the Cold War and US responses to them, as analyzed by Colonel William Kintner of the Foreign Policy Research Institute.
    Tab 2 Background Paper, U.S. Information Policy, prepared by Fritz G. A. Kraemer, December 23, 1959 -- analysis of the overseas information program of the US government, as analyzed by Dr. Fritz Kraemer of the Pentagon.
    Tab 3 Comparison of Republican and Democratic Platforms, Foreign Policy, General, September 9, 1960 -- summary positions and language of the two party platforms.
    Tab 4 Background Paper, Education for Democracy, February 8, 1961 -- paper on educational exchange programs, authored by J. L. Goldthwait.
    Tab 5 Summary of the State of the Union Message, Foreign Policy, General, January 18, 1962 -- analysis of President Kennedy's 1962 State of the Union speech as pertaining to foreign policy.
    Tab 6 Current Positions Cards, Foreign Policy, General, October 25, 1962 -- "talking points" for NAR to use in speeches.
    Tab 7 Background Paper, AFter Cuba, December 14, 1962 -- J. L. Goldthwait paper on Kennedy Foreign Policy in Cuba.
    Tab 8 NAR Answers for Associated Press Questionnaire, Foreign Policy, General, October 17, 1963 -- NAR responses to foreign policy questions in AP interview.
    Tab 9 Draft (#1) NAR Statement, St. Louis, Missouri, November 10, 1963 -- draft of NAR speech on foreign policy.
    Tab 10 NAR Statement, St. Louis, Missouri, November 16, 1963 -- transcript of NAR news conference in St. Louis.
  - Volume 8 - Foreign Policy, General, 1959-1964 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    Tab 11 Draft (#1) NAR Statement, "The Communist Challenge," January 6, 1964 -- draft of NAR speech on foreign policy, written by Henry Kissinger.
    Tab 12 Republican Platform, Foreign Policy, General, February 7, 1964 -- Republican Platform "plank" on foreign and defense policies.
    Tab 13 Newspaper Column, "How to Meet the Communist Challenge," February 13, 1964 -- press release of NAR column on US foreign policy and communism.
    Tab 14 California Republican Assembly Questionnaire, Foreign Policy, General, February 18, 1964 -- selected foreign policy questions posed to NAR by the California Republican Assembly.
    Tab 15 "Manchester (N.H.) Union-Leader" Questionnaire, Foreign Policy, General, February 18, 1964 -- selected foreign policy questions posed to NAR by the New Hampshire newspaper.
    Tab 16 Draft NAR Statement, Foreign Policy, General, March 1, 1964 -- draft of NAR speech to be used for foreign policy.
    Tab 17 NAR Statement, Foreign Policy, General, Washington, D.C., March 3, 1964 -- transcript of NAR news conference in Washington, D.C.
    Tab 18 Draft NAR Statement, Failures of Administration Foreign Policy, March 19, 1964 -- draft of NAR speech, written by Henry Kissinger on the failures of the Johnson administration in foreign policy.
    Tab 19 Draft (#1) NAR Statement, Union of the Free, March 25, 1964 -- draft of NAR speech, written by Henry Kissinger on the failure of the Johnson administration in foreign policy.
    Tab 20 Position Paper, Fulbright Attack on Administration Foreign Policy, March 31, 1964 -- response to Senator William Fulbright's attack on the Johnson administration's foreign policy.
    Tab 21 Answers for San Francisco "Monitor," Foreign Policy, General, May 7, 1964 -- selected foreign policy questions posed to NAR by the California Catholic newspaper.
    Tab 22 "As a Republican, I Believe... ," Foreign Policy, General, May 11, 1964 -- published brochure of NAR positions on issues affecting the United States and the Republican Party.
    Tab 23 Platform Analysis Notebook, Foreign Policy, General, May 1964 -- analysis of platform positions on issues of foreign policy.
    Tab 24 Draft NAR Statement, Administration Statements, May 19, 1964 -- draft statement on foreign policy positions of the Johnson Administration.
    Tab 25 NAR Statement, "The Communist Challenge" (revised), May 19, 1964 -- transcript of NAR remarks made at San Fernando State College, Northridge, California.
    Tab 26 Draft NAR Statement, Union of the Free, May 22, 1964 -- draft statement on foreign policy positions of the Johnson Administration.